Finding Aid for the Margery Turner Fisher Papers LSC.0355
UCLA Library Special Collections
Margery Turner Fisher papers
1937-1992
UCLA Library Special Collections
Fisher, Margery Turner
LSC.0355
98.5 Linear Feet (25 boxes, 2 cartons, and 42 oversize boxes)
Margery Turner Fisher (1913-1992) was an author and critic. She taught English at Oundle School (1939-45), organized courses on reading and writing for pleasure, and created her own journal, Growing point, for reviewing children's books. The collection consists of journals, annotated card index, illustrations, notes, correspondence, clippings, published books, manuscripts, maps, photographs, lectures, articles and reviews, and memorabilia.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942330233606533
Biography
Fisher was born Margery Turner in 1913 in Camberwell, London, England; B.Litt and MA from Somerville College, Oxford; became author and critic; taught English at Oundle School, 1939-45; organized courses on reading and writing for pleasure for the National Federation of Women's Institutes; in 1962, created her own journal, Growing point, for reviewing children's books; publications include Field day (1951), Intent upon reading: a critical appraisal of modern fiction for children (1961), Matters of fact: aspects of non-fiction for children (1972), Who's who in children's books (1975), and The bright face of danger (1986); she died on December 24, 1992 in Northampton, England.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of journals, annotated card index, illustrations, notes, correspondence, clippings, published books, manuscripts, maps, photographs, lectures, articles and reviews, and memorabilia.
Women periodical editors -- England -- Archives.; Women authors, English -- 20th century -- Archives.; Fisher, Margery Turner, 1913-1992--Archives.
- Administration
  - Address books and datebooks, 1970. (Box 48, Folder 5)
- Andre Deutsch (Publisher)
  - Correspondence, notes, 1973-1974. (Box 59, Folder 6)
- Articles and Reviews
  - In The Christian Science Monitor. Correspondence, clips, typescripts, 1966-1967. (Box 56, Folder 5)
  - In Mother magazine. Clips, correspondence, typescripts, 1967-1980. (Box 56, Folder 6)
  - In School Librarian. Clips, correspondence, typescripts, 1967-1969. (Box 56, Folder 7)
  - In Housewife magazine. Correspondence, notes, clips, 1951-1961. (Box 57, Folder 1)
  - In Signal. Correspondence, clips, typescript. Copies of magazine, 1956-1992. (Box 57, Folder 2)
  - Broadcast reviews on BBC World of Books and Network Three. Correspondence, typescripts, 1954-1965. (Box 57, Folder 3)
  - In the Sunday Times Christmas Pages. Correspondence. Clips in oversize box, 1966-77. (Box 57, Folder 4)
  - In the Sunday Times. Correspondence, clips, typescripts, 1966-1971. (Box 57, Folder 5)
  - In the Sunday Times. Correspondence, clips, typescripts, 1972-1984. (Box 57, Folder 6)
  - Reports on books for publishers A-L, 1989-1990. (Box 58, Folder 1)
  - Reports on books for publishers A-L, 1991-1992. (Box 58, Folder 2)
  - For Tyne Tees Television. Transcript, correspondence, reproductions of books, 1969. (Box 60, Folder 1)
  - For Jackanory. Correspondence, reports, 1966-1973. (Box 60, Folder 2)
  - For Brockhampton Press. Correspondence, typescripts, 1962-1972. (Box 60, Folder 8)
  - For Collins. Typescripts, 1953-1955. (Box 60, Folder 9)
  - Reports on children's books for publishers. Correspondence, typescripts, 1960-1972. (Box 61, Folder 1)
  - Reports on children's books for miscellaneous publishers. Correspondence, typescripts, 1960-1981. (Box 61, Folder 2)
  - Clippings of articles about children's literature, correspondence, research material, 1962-1989. (Box 62, Folder 2)
  - Published in Sunday Times, 1966-1977. (Box 66, Folder 3)
  - Adult Books
    - Correspondence, clips, typescripts, 1956-1980. (Box 56, Folder 4)
  - Children's Books
    - Correspondence, clips, typescript, notes, 1961-1979. (Box 56, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, clips, typescripts, 1962-1988. (Box 56, Folder 3)
- Author Bibliographies
  - Children's Fiction Go-He. (Box 7)
  - Children's Fiction Hea-Ja. (Box 8)
  - Children's Fiction Anonymous-Bak. (Box 1)
  - Children's Fiction Bal-Bon. (Box 2)
  - Children's Books Criticism & History A-Z. Poetry A-Z. (Box 20)
  - Children's Fiction Boon-Ce. (Box 3)
  - Children's Fiction Cha-Cz. (Box 4)
  - Children's Fiction D-E. (Box 5)
  - Children's Fiction F-Gi. (Box 6)
  - Children's Fiction Je-La. (Box 9)
  - Children's Fiction Le-Mac. (Box 10)
  - Children's Fiction Mas-My. (Box 11)
  - Children's Fiction N-Pi. (Box 12)
  - Children's Fiction Pl-Ro. (Box 13)
  - Children's Fiction Ru-Sq. (Box 14)
  - Children's Fiction St-To. (Box 15)
  - Children's Fiction Tr-Wik. (Box 16)
  - Children's Fiction Wil-Z. Adult Fiction A-Z. (Box 17)
- Bibliographies
  - MLEF research cards (5 boxes). (Box 32, Box 33, Box 34, Box 35, Box 36)
- Biography
  - Resume. (Box 69, Folder 1)
- Books
  - Born a Victorian
    - The memories of L.E. Turner. Manuscript, 1964. (Box 59, Folder 2)
    - Typescript. (Box 59, Folder 3)
  - Bright Face of Danger
    - Reviews, 1986. (Box 53, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1986-1987. (Box 53, Folder 2)
    - Working notes, general correspondence with publishers, (?)., covers 1961-1985 (Box 53, Folder 3)
    - General research material, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 4)
    - Research material on characters (the hero), n.d. (Box 53, Folder 5)
    - Research material on settings in space and futuristic adventures (Box 53, Folder 6)
    - Research material on biography and autobiography (Box 53, Folder 7)
    - Research material on settings in Africa, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 8)
    - Listings of adventure books according to date published, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 9)
    - Research material on themes and conventions. 3/4 Aggression theory and research, violence in fiction, comics, tv series, adult and junior detective stories, politics and thrillers, spy and war stories (Box 53, Folder 10)
    - Research material on settings or under themes: 3/4 Ruritania, chivalry and honor, cloak and dagger, history pastiches, Northwest frontier, military honour, Jacobites (Box 53, Folder 11)
    - Research material on criticism of adventure genre, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 12)
    - General research material, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 13)
    - Research on narrative technique, style, and voice (Box 53, Folder 14)
    - Research material on serials: 3/4 Flash Gordon, Dan Dare and the magazines which carried serials like Collins magazine for Boys and Girls (Box 53, Folder 15)
    - Research material on criticism and theories of fiction (Box 54, Folder 1)
    - Research material on the psychological effects of adventure, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 2)
    - Research material on education and morality (Box 54, Folder 3)
    - Research material on critical attitudes, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 4)
    - Research material on characters (the villain), n.d. (Box 54, Folder 5)
    - Research material on characters (children in groups, serials and sequences) (Box 54, Folder 6)
    - Research material on minor characters: The solitary horseman, the car, the omniscient uncle, the faithful servant, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 7)
    - Research material on South American settings: Revolution and treasure (Box 54, Folder 8)
    - Footnotes (?), Chapters 1-16, Manuscript Draft, Chapters 1-7, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 9)
    - Manuscript with note to publisher. Chapters 8-16, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 10)
    - Research materials on juvenile themes, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 11)
    - Research material on critic's attitudes towards depictions of women, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 12)
    - Research materials on critic's attitudes toward racist depictions, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 13)
    - Research materials on travel adventures, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 14)
    - Research material on the depictions of geographical frontiers - Wild West, Red Indians, New Zealand, Australia (Box 54, Folder 15)
    - Studies of market values and best seller lists (Box 54, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous notes on individual authors (Box 54, Folder 17)
    - Adventure stories reading lists, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 1)
    - Research material on stories set at sea, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 2)
    - Carbons of discarded manuscript sheets, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 3)
    - First Draft. Book 1, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 4)
    - First Draft. Book 2, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 5)
    - First Draft. Book 3, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 6)
  - Classics for Children and Young Adults
    - Research material on historical fiction, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 2)
    - Research material, correspondence, 1960-1972. (Box 65, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, n.d. (Box 61, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence with Signal (publisher), publicity and research materials, 1983-1986. (Box 61, Folder 8)
    - Copy of published work, 1986. (Box 62, Folder 1)
    - Research material [newsprint], n.d. (Box 65, Folder 4)
  - Field Day
    - Reviews and correspondence: 3/4 Including J.B. Priestley, Cony Beare, Julian Huxley, 1951-1952. (Box 64, Folder 9)
  - Henry Treece
    - Correspondence and notes, 1967-1971. (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - Intent Upon Reading
    - Correspondence, notes, 1959-1962. (Box 64, Folder 7)
    - Reviews, 1961. (Box 64, Folder 8)
  - John Masefield
    - Letters received from John Masefield, 1963. (Box 60, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, clips, 1960-1967. (Box 60, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, research material, print of John Masefield (Box 60, Folder 7)
  - Journeys
    - Discarded pieces, clippings, correspondence, notes, 1972-1973. (Box 64, Folder 6)
  - Matters of Fact
    - Correspondence, notes, 1965-1973. (Box 64, Folder 10)
    - Reviews and correspondence, 1967-1976. (Box 65, Folder 1)
  - Memoirs of a London Doll
    - Research material, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 7)
    - Letters and notes (Box 55, Folder 8)
    - Photocopies of three letters from R.H. Horne to Edgar Allen Poe, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence and reviews of MF's introduction, 1961. (Box 55, Folder 10)
    - Letters from Horne to Carndale 1844-46. Microfilm (Box 69, Folder 4)
  - Open the Door
    - Reviews, correspondence, 1963-1976. (Box 64, Folder 3)
    - American edition. Reviews and correspondence, 1966-1968. (Box 64, Folder 4)
  - The House on Water Street
    - Correspondence, 1986-1990. (Box 58, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, n.d. (Box 58, Folder 4)
  - The Hut
    - Synopsis, maps, photographs, letters, 1961. (Box 58, Folder 7)
  - Who's Who in Children's Literature
    - Correspondence re: reprint and additions, 1986-1987. (Box 63, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, notes, 1972-1985. (Box 63, Folder 10)
    - Discarded pieces, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 1)
    - Reviews, publicity, letters from readers, 1975-1977. (Box 64, Folder 2)
  - Women Sewing
    - Original version of part two, n.d. (Box 58, Folder 8)
  - World of Animals
    - Reviews and correspondence, 1961-1962. (Box 64, Folder 5)
- Center for Children's Literature
  - Correspondence, 1968-1992. (Box 59, Folder 5)
- Children's Book Centre
  - Articles submitted, 1964-1965. (Box 59, Folder 7)
- Conference on Recent Children's Fiction
  - University of Exeter, 1969-71. (Box 62, Folder 6)
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, 1962-1992. (Box 59, Folder 11)
- Denham College Courses
  - Clippings and programs, 1959-1965. (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - Syllabi, correspondence, lists of students, evaluations, 1959-1965. (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - Syllabi, correspondence, evaluations, lists of students, programs, 1964-1968. (Box 63, Folder 5)
  - Syllabi, correspondence, evaluations, lists of students, 1966-1973. (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - Syllabi, correspondence, lists of students, programs, evaluations, 1973-1984. (Box 63, Folder 7)
- Eleanor Farjeon Award
  - Correspondence, clips, 1966. (Box 60, Folder 4)
- Growing Point
  - Letters from subscribers, 1961-1968. (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Letters from subscribers, 1962-1974. (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Letters from subscribers, 1962-1976. (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Letters from subscribers, 1967-1992. (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Letters from subscribers, 1962-1969. (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Letters from subscribers, 1962-1967. (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Letters from subscribers, 1968-1989. (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Letters from subscribers, 1965-1985. (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Letters from subscribers, 1971-1974. (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Letters from subscribers, 1979-1990. (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Letters from subscribers, 1977-1991. (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - Letters from subscribers - re the end of publication of Growing Point, 1992. (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Letters and materials from contributors. File 1 of 5, 1964-1988. (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Letters and materials from contributors. File 2 of 5, 1963-1990. (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Letters and materials from contributors. File 3 of 5, 1963-1990. (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Letters and materials from contributors. File 4 of 5, 1962-1967. (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Letters and materials from contributors. File 5 of 5, 1969-1979. (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with illustrator Trevor Stubley, 1976-1977. (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence re: production of the magazine, 1962-1984. (Box 39, Folder 8)
  - Letters from authors-Including Philippa Pearce, Andre Norton, Faith Jacques, John Rowe Townsend, 1966-1990. (Box 39, Folder 9)
  - General correspondence (Box 39, Folder 10)
  - Bank sheets and receipted bills, 1970. (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Bank statements, foreign conversions, check stubs, 1973-1974. (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - Bank statements, foreign statements, check stubs, 1974-1975. (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - Receipted bills, bank statements, check stubs, 1975-1976. (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Bank statements, check stubs, receipted bills, 1976. (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Bank statements, check stubs, receipted bills, 1976-1977. (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Bank statements, check stubs, receipted bills, 1980-1981. (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - Disallowable domestic expenses, 1976. (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - Allowable domestic expenses, 1976. (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - Receipts - car, 1976-1977. (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - Sample subscription form, n.d. (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - Estimates for the production of Growing Point, 1966. (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - Circulation figures, 1964-1990. (Box 41, Folder 7)
  - Bibliographies of books for review, 1983-1991. (Box 41, Folder 11)
  - Bibliographies of books received for review, 1974-1983. (Box 41, Folder 12)
  - Bibliography for Old Favorites feature, 1962-1989. (Box 41, Folder 13)
  - Cash receipts records, April 1973-March 1976. (Box 42)
  - Cash receipts records, July 1975-June 1992. (Box 43)
  - Printing blocks for illustrations, n.d. (Box 44)
  - Printing blocks for illustrations, n.d. (Box 45)
  - Printing blocks for illustrations, n.d. (Box 46)
  - Typescript and galley proofs (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - Subscription reminders (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - Posthumous orders, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Letter and address books (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - Letter books, 1971-1979. (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - Illustrations for Growing Point, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 6)
  - Letter from Publishers A-G, 1962-1992. (Box 47, Folder 7)
  - Letters from Publishers H-R, 1962-1992. (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Publishers S-W (end), 1964-1992. (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Reviews received for Growing Point and Intent Upon Reading, 1962-1966. (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - Letters received with reviews and list of places to send for reviews (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - Publications vol.1-15 set 1-A complete run of Growing Point does not exist in this collection, n.d. (Box 49)
  - Publications vol.16-30 set 1, n.d. (Box 50)
  - Publications vol.1-15 set 2, n.d. (Box 51)
  - Publications vol.16-30 set 2, n.d. (Box 52)
- International Board for Books for Young People (IBBY)
  - Conference. Nice. Correspondence, notes for report, 1971-1972. (Box 61, Folder 5)
  - Hans Christian Andersen Medal, 1967-1973. (Box 61, Folder 6)
  - Committee reports, photographs, correspondence, 1969-1982. (Box 61, Folder 3)
  - Hans Christian Andersen Award. Correspondence, information about nominees and winners, 1961-1978. (Box 61, Folder 4)
- Introductions, Forewords
  - Correspondence, typescripts, 1964-1970. (Box 59, Folder 10)
- Items Collected
  - Blank notecards, n.d. (Box 41, Folder 8)
  - Goosecards with messages from friends and family (Box 41, Folder 9)
  - James Thurber cartoons clipped from the New Yorker, c. 1930. (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - Charles Madge's poems and articles, 1937-1939. (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - Sally Benson essays and James Thurber cartoons, 1937. (Box 66, Folder 2)
  - Death Comes to the Party. Sound recording (Box 69, Folder 2)
- Lecture Tour/Lectures
  - Australia
    - Correspondence, clippings, typescript of speech, 1975. (Box 62, Folder 5)
  - New Zealand
    - Correspondence, clippings, transcript of interview, 1972. (Box 62, Folder 4)
  - International Summer Seminar on Children's Literature
    - Baltimore, Maryland. Correspondence, notes, program, 1973. (Box 62, Folder 8)
  - Lecture: Mary Hill Arbuthnot
    - Correspondence, typescript of lectures, lecture programs, 1969-1970. (Box 63, Folder 2)
  - Santillana Conference
    - Madrid. Minutes of meeting, correspondence, photographs, 1971. (Box 62, Folder 3)
  - Lectures on Children's Books
    - Typescripts and list of lectures, 1956-1975. (Box 62, Folder 7)
  - Lectures on Various Authors
    - Notes 3/4 On Ivy Compton Burnett, Horace Walpole, Edith Wharton, etc., c1960. (Box 58, Folder 6)
  - International Research Society for Children's literature
    - Exeter 1978. Bordeaux 1983. Correspondence, typescript of lecture, meeting program, 1978-1983. (Box 63, Folder 1)
- Letters Received
  - from authors---Nina Bawden, Gillian Avery, A.S. Byatt. Faith Jacques, Philippa Pearce, B.B. Watkins Pitchford, Zohar Shavit, Pamela Sykes, 1956-1992. (Box 59, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous Fiction
  - Notes, n.d. (Box 59, Folder 1)
- Monograph: Notes on the Sources of Some of Middleton's London Plays
  - Copies of publication, 1939. (Box 58, Folder 5)
- National Book League
  - Correspondence, copies of publications, 1958-1967. (Box 60, Folder 3)
- Publications Collected
  - Miscellaneous journals: Signal, The Junior Bookshelf, Phaedrus, n.d. (Box 67)
  - Miscellaneous journals and bibliographies: Bookbird, Top of the News, Horn Book, Children's Literature Abstracts (Box 68)
- Reprints
  - Correspondence advocating reprints of particular children's books, 1981-1982. (Box 59, Folder 8)
- Research Material
  - Offprints of literary criticism, n.d. (Box 48, Folder 8)
  - Articles on practice of criticism of children's books, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 5)
  - Clippings about writing style and children's literature, 1961-1983. (Box 66, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Willa and Mary Howitt to Eliza Noteyard 1847. Microfilm (Box 69, Folder 3)
- Retirement
  - Letters received, clips, 1992. (Box 59, Folder 4)
- Short Stories and Synopses
  - Correspondence, clips, typescripts, c. 1940. (Box 58, Folder 9)
- Souvenir: The Journal of the Violet Needham Society
  - Copies of publication, 1990-1992. (Box 63, Folder 8)
- Subject Bibliographies
  - Children's Fiction. Notebooks 1-39. Each notebook has a different subject. (Box 18)
  - Information Books: History/Geography, Exploration, Biography & Autobiography. Junior Concept Books. (Box 21)
  - Information Books: History/Geography, Religions. (Box 22)
  - Information Books: Science. (Box 23)
  - Information Books: Hobbies/Activities. (Box 24)
  - Information Books: Education, Careers, Poetry 85/86, Dolls, Arts. Four notebook bibliographies: Growing Point (Titles of Features, reminders, special reviews, blocks used, Old Favorites). (Box 25)
  - Information Books: Transport/Communciations, Technology, Technology & Social Life, Institutions. (Box 26)
  - Information Books Unsorted (3 boxes). (Box 27, Box 28, Box 29)
  - [Fiction] Unsorted (3 boxes). (Box 29, Box 30, Box 31)
  - 19th century children's books, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 11)
  - Bibliography card file dividers not used, n.d. (Box 41, Folder 10)
- Subject/Publisher Bibliographies
  - Animal Stories A-Z. Richard Hengist Horne. Information Books (subject) Agriculture, Archeology, Anthropology, Biology, Exploration, Geography, History, Literature, Music, Miscellaneous Information, Natural History, etc. Information Books (publishers) A-Z. (Box 19)